A Guide to the A. O. Wright Collection of Confederate Navy service records, 1922-1925
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A. O. Wright Collection of Confederate Navy service Records, 1922-1925
Library of Virginia
20976
25 leaves and 25 pages
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of A. O. Wright of St. Augustine, Florida, 1925.
Biographical Information
Augustus O. Wright was born 18 March 1844 in Greensboro, Alabama. He was a midshipman in the Naval Academy when the Civil War began. He resigned from the Academy 22 April 1861, and joined the Confederate navy. Wright was appointed acting midshipman 7 December 1861 and midshipman 2 June 1864. Wright served on the Savannah station from 1861 to 1862 and was part of the defense of Fort Fisher, North Carolina, from 1864 to 1865. He served on various naval vessels and ended the war as a member of Semmes' Naval Brigade in 1865. After the war, Wright was a judge in Florida. He also organized the veterans of the Confederate navy into a branch of the United Confederate Veterans. His efforts garnered him the honorary title of admiral. Wright died in St. Augustine, Florida, 5 September 1928. He had a wife and two daughters.
Scope and Content
Collection of Confederate Navy service records, 1922-1925, of A. O. Wright (1844-1928) of St. Augustine, Florida, containing correspondence, reminiscenses, questionnaires, and lists relating to his efforts to obtain military records of men who served in the Confederate States Navy. This collection pertains to Virginians who served in that branch.
Arrangement
Arranged partially chronologically.
Contents List
- Letter, 22 July 1922, from Annie B. Camm, Richmond, Virginia, to A. O. Wright, in Richmond, discussing Wright's efforts to compile the records of Confederate sailors., 4 pages.
- Letter, 19 June 1922, from Susan Stribling Snodgrass, Martinsburg, West Virginia, to A. O. Wright, regarding the Confederate naval service of John Maxwell Stribling aboard the Florida during the Civil War., 7 pages.
- Letter, 2 December 1922, from G. Cabell Chambliss, Bristol, Tennessee, to A. O. Wright in Richmond, Virginia, concerning the Confederate naval service of Joseph Miller Gardner aboard the Tallahassee during the Civil War., 1 leaf.
- Letter, 1 December 1922, from Samuel M. Chappell, Richmond, to A. O. Wright, containing the reminiscences of his father John T. Chappell of Richmond, who served aboard the Patrick Henry and the Virginia during his service in the Confederate Navy., 4 leaves.
- Reminiscences, n.d., of John Bondurant Gardner of Bedford County, Virginia, about his service aboard the Richmond while in the Confederate Navy. He also recalls the burning of Richmond and his journey home to Danville, Virginia., 3 leaves.
- Reminiscences, n.d., of John A. Curtis of Richmond about his service aboard the spar torpedo-boat Squib while in the Confederate Navy., 3 leaves.
- Reminiscences, n.d., of John A. Curtis of Richmond about his service aboard the Tallahassee while in the Confederate Navy., 3 leaves.
- Questionaire, n.d., filled in regarding the Confederate naval service of Richard H. B. English aboard the Patrick Henry. Includes a copy of the resolution passed by several states including Virginia to encourage A. O. Wright's work of collecting the history of Confederate sailors., 2 pages.
- Questionaire, n.d., filled in regarding the Confederate naval service of J. B. Moess of Richmond aboard the Virginia. Includes a copy of the resolution passed by several states including Virginia to encourage A. O. Wright's work of collecting the history of Confederate sailors., 2 pages.
- Questionaire, n.d., filled in regarding the Confederate naval service of J. G. Boxley of Orange County, Virginia. Includes a copy of the resolution passed by the state of Virginia encouraging A. O. Wright's efforts to collect the history of Confederate sailors., 2 pages.
- Letter, 31 March 1924, from H. R. McIlwaine, State Librarian of Virginia, Richmond, for A. O. Wright, to E. H. Rouse of Orange County thanking him for submitting the questionaire on J. G. Boxley., 1 leaf.
- Questionaire, n.d., regarding the Confederate naval service of John Bondurant Gardner of Bedford County. Includes a copy of the resolution passed by the state of Virginia encouraging A. O. Wright's efforts to collect the history of Confederate sailors., 2 pages.
- Letter, 2 September 1924, from H. R. McIlwaine, State Librarian, for A. O. Wright, to John Bondurant Gardner, Bedford County, thanking him for submitting a questionaire., 1 leaf.
- Questionaire, n.d., filled in on a Captain Higgins of Crittenden, Virginia. Includes a copy of the resolution passed by the state of Virginia encouraging A. O. Wright's efforts to collect the history of Confederate sailors., 2 pages.
- Questionaire, n.d., filled in on Captain A. M. Morecock of Claremont, Virginia. Includes a copy of the resolution passed by the state of Virginia encouraging A. O. Wright's efforts to collect the history of Confederate sailors., 2 pages.
- Letter, 23 July 1924, from H. R. McIlwaine, State Librarian, for A. O. Wright, to H. L. Harris, James City County, Virginia, thanking him for the questionaires on Captain Higgins and Captain A. M. Morecock., 1 leaf.
- List, 23 September 1924, of records mailed to Richmond, Virginia., 1 leaf.
- List, 7 November 1924, of names of men whose Confederate naval records Wright had obtained., 1 leaf.
- List, 4 December 1924, of names of men who served in Confederate Navy., 1 leaf.
- Letter, 3 January 1925, from W. H. McElroy, Shreveport, Louisiana, to H. R. McIlvainey (H. R. McIlwaine), Richmond, containing a list of names of men from Virginia who served in the Confederate Navy., 1 leaf.
- List, 31 January 1925, of names of men who served in the Confederate Navy., 1 leaf.
- List, 31 March 1925, of names of men who served in the Naval Branch of the Confederacy sent to Virginia., 2 pages.
- List, 6 May 1925, of names of men who served in the Confederate Navy., 1 leaf.
- Citation, n.d., for volume I, series II of the Official Record of the War of the Rebellion: Union and Confederate soldiers of the Navy and army 1862 to 1865., 1 leaf.
- List, n.d., of names of men in the Confederate Navy and includes their rank or position., 1 leaf.